Jay Henderson Curriculum Vitae

Pronouns: he/any Nationality: Canadian

Email: jayhend [at] mun.ca Website: jayhenderson.ca

Current Position

Assistant Professor Department of Computer Science, Memorial University of Newfoundland

Overview

My research interests span a variety of domains within human-computer interaction, including, learning input techniques, augmented/mixed/virtual reality, and 2D/3D interaction – with the overarching goal of understanding human behaviour while interacting with emerging technology. My fundamental computer science background paired with interdisciplinary training in psychology and mathematics has placed me in a unique position to make meaningful contributions to the field: evident through my numerous publications at top-tier venues.

Education

PhD in Computer Science 2021

Thesis: Understanding Mode and Modality Transfer in Unistroke Gesture Input

University of Waterloo

BSc Hons in Computer Science (minors in Mathematics and Psychology) 2016

Mount Allison University

Professional Experience

2023 -Assistant Professor

Memorial University of Newfoundland

2022 - 2023 Postdoctoral Fellow & Instructor

Carleton University

2021 - 2022 Senior Research Scientist

Huawei Technologies Canada

- 2019 2020 Research Scientist Internship

 Meta Reality Labs (formerly Chatham Labs)
- 2018 2019 Research Scientist Internship Huawei Technologies Canada
- 2017 Visiting Researcher *Inria, Lille*
- 2016 Software Engineer

 Mysa Smart Thermostats

Publications

- *** Note about venues: in Human-Computer Interaction (HCI), conference proceedings are the preferred publication venues, being timelier and having the greatest impact (typical for experimental computer science). Top tier conferences require rigorous multi-stage review of manuscripts for archival proceedings. CHI (ACM's Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems) and IMWUT (The Proceedings of the ACM on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies) are ranked #1 and #3, respectively, in HCI (via Google Scholar).
- Jay Henderson, Ali Neshati, Wei Zhou, Daniel Vogel, Edward Lank. 2023. *Interaction Region Characteristics for Midair Barehand Targeting on a Television.*Extended Abstracts of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI EA '23).

DOI: 10.1145/3544549.3585877. (Acceptance rate: 34%)

Arman Hafizi, **Jay Henderson**, Ali Neshati, Wei Zhou, Edward Lank, Daniel Vogel. 2023. *In-vehicle Performance and Distraction for Midair and Touch Directional Gestures*. In Proceedings of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '23).

DOI: 10.1145/3544548.3581335. (Acceptance rate: 28.4%)

Jay Henderson, Tanya Jonker, Edward Lank, Daniel Wigdor, Ben Lafreniere. 2022. Investigating Cross-Modal Approaches for Evaluating Error Acceptability of a Recognition-Based Input Technique. In Proc. ACM Interact. Mob. Wearable Ubiquitous Technol. 6, 1 (March 2022), 22 pages.

DOI: 10.1145/3517262. (Average acceptance rate: 22.5%)

Jay Henderson, Jessy Ceha, and Edward Lank. 2020. STAT: Subtle Typing Around the Thigh for Head-Mounted Displays. In 22nd International Conference on Human-Computer Interaction with Mobile Devices and Services (MobileHCI '20). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, Article 27, 1–11. DOI: 10.1145/3379503.3403549. (Average acceptance rate: 23.1%)

Jay Henderson, Sylvain Malacria, Mathieu Nancel, and Edward Lank. 2020. *Investigating The Necessity Of Delay In Marking Menu Invocation*. In Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '20), Apr 25–30, 2020, Honolulu, HI USA. Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, 1–13.

DOI: 10.1145/3313831.3376296. (Acceptance rate: 24.3%)

Jay Henderson, Sachi Mizobuchi, Wei Li, and Edward Lank. 2019. Exploring Cross-Modal Training via Touch to Learn a Mid-Air Marking Menu Gesture Set. In Proceedings of the 21st International Conference on Human-Computer Interaction with Mobile Devices and Services (MobileHCl '19). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, Article 8, 1–9.

DOI: 10.1145/3338286.3340119. (Average acceptance rate: 23.1%)

Jay Henderson, Jeff Avery, Laurent Grisoni, and Edward Lank. 2019. Leveraging Distal Vibrotactile Feedback for Target Acquisition. In Proceedings of the 2019 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '19), May 4–9, 2019, Glasgow, Scotland UK. ACM, New York, NY, USA 11 Pages.

DOI: 10.1145/3290605.3300715. (Acceptance rate: 23.8%)

Jay Henderson, Shaishav Siddhpuria, Keiko Katsuragawa, and Edward Lank. 2017. Fostering large display engagement through playful interactions. In Proceedings of the 6th ACM International Symposium on Pervasive Displays (PerDis '17). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, Article 20, 1–8.

DOI: 10.1145/3078810.3078818. (Acceptance rate: 55%)

Service

2021 - Program Committee (Associate Chair)

Graphics Interface

ACM's DIS (Designing Interactive Systems)

ACM's CHI Late Breaking Work

ACM's MobileHCI Late Breaking Work

2018 - Peer Reviewer

ACM CHI (Human Factors in Computing Systems)

ACM MobileHCI (Mobile Human-Computer Interaction)

ACM AutoUI (Automotic User Interfaces)

ACM DIS (Designing Interactive Systems)

ACM ISS (Interactive Surfaces and Spaces)

ACM ETRA (Eye Tracking Research & Applications)

ACM SUI (Spatial User Interfaces)

IEEE ISMAR (International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality)

IEEE VR (Virtual Reality and 3D User Interfaces

Elsevier IJCHS (International Journal of Human Computer Studies)

2019 ACM Name Change Committee

Association for Computing Machinery

As a transgender person, I was selected to serve on a committee that developed an overarching name change policy within all ACM publications.

(https://www.acm.org/publications/policies/author-name-changes)

2019 CHI Conference Allyship Program

ACM SIGCHI

Served as a point of contact for attendees about equity. Selected for experience in equity-related activities, particularly, involvement in LGBTQ+ initiatives.

2017 CHI Conference Student Volunteer

ACM SIGCHI

2014 - 2016 S.M.I.L.E. Buddy

Mount Allison University / Cumberland YMCA

An accessibility oriented buddy program offered to children with disabilities, who may otherwise not be able to participate in typical programs due to their unique developmental needs. Occurred each Saturday morning of the academic year.

Teaching

2023 ITEC 4011 – AI for Digital Media Instructor & Course Developer

Carleton University

2018 - 2020 CS 349 - Introduction to User Interfaces

Instructional Apprentice *University of Waterloo*

2017 - 2019 CS 105 - Introduction to Computer Programming 1

Instructional Apprentice University of Waterloo

2017 - 2018 CS 106 - Introduction to Computer Programming 2

Instructional Apprentice University of Waterloo

2019 CS 449/649 – Human-Computer Interaction

TΑ

University of Waterloo

2016 CS 135 – Designing Functional Programs

TA

University of Waterloo

2016	COMP 1731 – Programming Techniques and Algorithms TA Mount Allison University
2015	COMP 2931 – Introduction to Systems Programming TA Mount Allison University
	Awards and Funding
2023	Postdoctoral Fellow Professional Development Fund Valued at \$2000 for travel to ACM's 2023 CHI conference.
2017 - 2019	David R. Cheriton Graduate Scholarship Awarded by the director of the Cheriton School of Computer Science and an appointed committee based on academic excellence. Valued at \$10,000 annually (\$20,000/2 years).
2016 - 2021	Math Graduate Student Award Valued at \$6,000 annually (\$30,000/5 years).
2016 - 2021	Graduate Student Research Travel Assistantship Valued at \$500 for travel to various conferences.
	Supervision
2023	Danielle Cole, Carleton University BIT Student The Mixed and Augmented Reality and Virtual Environments Lab
2023	Elis Joynes, Carleton University BIT Student The Mixed and Augmented Reality and Virtual Environments Lab
2022	Arman Hafizi, University of Waterloo MMath Student (Informal co-supervision) Huawei-Waterloo Joint Innovation Lab
2022	Jeffrey Lee, Mechatronics Engineering Co-op Student Human-Machine Interaction Lab, Huawei Technologies Canada
2022	Rachel Du, Mechatronics Engineering Co-op Student Human-Machine Interaction Lab, Huawei Technologies Canada